The Henry Clay Family
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Part II: Miscellany, ca. 1793-1922, n.d. (Box II:60-64)
  Address books, calling cards, circulars, cookbooks, drawings, genealogies, inventories, journal, lists, maps, mementos, newspaper clippings, notes, obituaries, printed matter, reports, scrapbooks, sketches, speeches, and transcriptions.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Drawings and sketches, 1882, n.d. (Box II:60)
  - Genealogies, 1832-1919, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Journal, containing original collection inventory, critique of Andrew Jackson administration, and "Alphonse, or Natural Son," ca. 1829-1871, n.d.
  - Mementos, calling cards, and address book, 1852-1883, n.d. (Box II:61)
  - Newspaper clippings, ca. 1856-1917, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box II:62, Box II:63)
  - Notes, lists, transcriptions, and inventories
    - ca. 1793-1922, n.d.
  - Printed matter, ca. 1828-1922, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box II:64)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Henry Clay, ca. 1835-1914, n.d.
    - Clay family, ca. 1880-1921, n.d.
    - Civil War, ca. 1861-1862, n.d.
- Part II: Legal File, 1732-1857, n.d. (Box II:65-66)
  Articles of agreement, assignments, bills of complaint, deeds, depositions, indentures, land claims, land grants, land patents, legal memoranda, legal opinions, plats, pleas, powers of attorney, surveys, summons, treasury warrants, and wills.
  - Dec. 1732-July 1801, (5 folders) (Box II:65)
  - Aug. 1801-Aug. 1857, n.d., (3 folders) (Box II:66)
- Part II: James Morrison Papers, 1790-1849, n.d. (Box II:66-74)
  Correspondence, including letters received and copies of letters sent with attached bills and receipts; business records, including accounts payable, accounts receivable, bills of lading, bonds, indentures, legal records, promissory notes, receipts, and tax records; and estate papers.
  - Business correspondence (Box II:66)
    - Correspondence
      - Nov. 1795-Dec. 1807, (3 folders)
      - Jan. 1808-Feb. 1810, (6 folders) (Box II:67)
      - Mar. 1810-Aug. 1816, (6 folders) (Box II:68)
      - Sept. 1816-Sept. 1822, (6 folders) (Box II:69)
      - Oct. 1822-Aug. 1823 (Box II:70)
    - Envelopes, annotated wrappings, etc., ca. 1795-1823, n.d.
  - Business records
    - Aug. 1790-Nov. 1808, (5 folders)
    - Dec. 1808-Dec. 1810, (7 folders) (Box II:71)
    - Jan. 1811-Feb. 1816, (7 folders) (Box II:72)
    - Mar. 1816-Aug. 1823, n.d., (5 folders) (Box II:73)
  - Estate papers
    - Feb. 1823-June 1829, (2 folders)
    - July 1829-Jan. 1849 (Box II:74)
- Part II: George Nicholas Papers, 1777-1831, n.d. (Box II:74-75)
  Client and business files including articles of agreement, bills of complaint, financial records, indentures, land claims, legal memoranda, pleas, receipts, and wills; correspondence, primarily professional and business letters received; and estate papers containing wills, financial records, and legal documents.
  - Client and business file, 1777-1779, n.d., (2 folders) (Box II:74)
  - Correspondence, 1782-1799, (2 folders)
  - Estate papers
    - 1797-1825, (2 folders)
    - 1826-31 (Box II:75)
- Part II: Transylvania University Archives, 1829-1868, n.d. (Box II:75)
  Account records, articles of agreement, bank checks, correspondence, minutes, promissory notes, and receipts.
  - Records, 1829-1868, n.d., (5 folders) (Box II:75)
- Part II: Addenda, 1837-1847 (Box II:75)
  Correspondence.
  - Correspondence, 1837-1847 (Box II:75)
- Part II: Microfilm (Reel 9-24)
  Microfilm of Clay papers miscellany, card index to correspondence, items from Containers 34-39, and Clay material from other collections.
  Arrangement described in finding aid to microfilm edition.
  Microfilm shelf nos. 13,789, 13,789.1, and 17,343.
  - Clay papers miscellany (Reel 9)
  - Reproductions from Containers 41-49 (Reel 10-19)
  - Selections from other Manuscript Division collections (Reel 20-23)
  - Card index to correspondence (Reel 24)